Welcome back to another video with
ItsDrdan, and today we're gonna be
looking at the oxidation of alcohols.
So with alcohols, they go through a common
reaction where the oxygen is going to be
changing to different functional groups.
So how are these all shown?
Well, with our first example,
one thing that you are noticing
is that we have a alcohol here.
Reacting with something
that is an O in brackets.
So what exactly does that represent?
So that way before we kind of
continue here, if you were to ever
see an O in brackets, that is always
representing the oxidizing agent.
So meaning that this is what is
causing the oxidation reaction.
Okay.
So it is our chaos agent.
It causes the reaction.
With this, how exactly do you generally
see that O Well, O can mean it, it
depends on exactly which reagent is,
it is, uh, actually reacting here.
'cause it can cause either a mild or
a strong oxidation depending on how
far it's gonna push the reaction.
So let's go into it and let's try to
explain how that is going to work.
So with our first one, what
exactly are we trying to do here?
So I have three different alcohols
that each have a slightly different
structure to them, and our first thing
that we are going to do is classify our
alcohols because that that shows exactly
which reaction is going to take place.
So how exactly do we go about classifying?
Well, what we're always gonna
be looking at is looking at
our alcohol or our oh, group.
And we're going to look at the carbon
that is directly next to the, oh.
So I'm gonna put a little star
next to all those carbons.
Now what you will do is count how
what, how many oxygen or how many
carbons are directly next to it.
So for this first one, we can see
that we have one carbon next to it.
So what this is, this
is a primary alcohol.
Versus the second one here.
Well, if I do the same general
idea, we're gonna count one carbon
on the left, or sorry on the right,
and then one carbon on the left.
And that means that we have two, right?
So it's gonna be secondary or two prime.
So two prime is a secondary alcohol.
Now what about the last one?
Well, the last one is
the same general idea.
We're gonna count our carbons all around.
So we have one here, one up
top, and then another one all
the way on the far side here.
So we have a total of three prime
or a tertiary alcohol, and those
are the three types of alcohols
that you're going to commonly see.
So what exactly is going to happen here?
Well, let's try to dive in a little
bit more closely to our first or
primary alcohol before we continue
to fill in this exact chart
with a primary alcohol.
The big difference here of what
we are seeing, it's all about how
is the functional group changing.
So I highlighted the functional group here
in blue for the alcohol to show that this
is going to be going through a reaction.
Now, more specifically, what is
happening here is we're gonna be going
through a de hydrogenation reaction.
So we're gonna be removing hydrogen.
So when we look at this, we have a
hydrogen that's connected to the alcohol.
And we're gonna remove one hydrogen
from the carbon next to it.
So when that happens, we're
removing both of those two species.
So they're gonna go, they're
gonna disconnect and go away.
Now when that happens, well,
what group can possibly form?
Well, what we're going to do is
we're gonna redraw our chain, right?
So we had those four carbons, and in
order to fulfill that bond, So if I
take my structure here, so, and just
recopy this hydro or oxygen have, if
you look closely here and here you'll
see that these bonds are not happy.
Carbon has to have four bonds.
It currently has three oxygen
needs, two, it has one.
So what are we gonna do is we are going
to form a double bond to help change that.
So when that changes, We'll be going
from an, uh, alcohol to an aldehyde.
So we're gonna be adding that double
bond and changing our structure.
Now, this is referred to as
a mild oxidation, meaning
that we are a weak oxidation.
We went one step with primary
alcohols, they can go one more step.
So with this same general
ideas, it can keep going.
And we can add to our double
oh to make add an oh to the end
and create a carboxylic acid.
So we can go from an
aldehyde to carboxylic acid.
If it goes all the way, this
is referred to as strong versus
weak, which is only one step.
So depending on how far are you pushing.
Those boundaries.
So the oxidation most of the time will
go all the way unless you're given
what is referred to as a mild oxidizing
agent, which is specified in the homework
or exam problems, or even in the lab.
So let's put this onto our original
chart and continue this idea.
Okay, so now we filled in our first part.
We can see that, that a primary
alcohol can have two reaction steps.
So how exactly can we tell how
many reactions can this have?
Let's fill in our secondary alcohol
and then our tertiary, and I'll show
you all the patterns that we have here.
So for secondary alcohol, it's still
gonna be the same general idea.
We're gonna remove a hydrogen from
the carbon that the alcohol's attached
to, as well as from the alcohol.
And we're still gonna be
adding that C double bond O.
So in this case, we're
going to be making a ketone.
Now, this is, as far as this reaction
goes, it does not go any farther
now with a tertiary compound.
Well, it's the same idea.
We have to remove a hydrogen from
the carbon adjacent to the alcohol.
But one thing about this is,
you might have already noticed,
is that, well, we already have.
All four bonds around that carbon,
which had the star next to it.
So this particular one,
it has all four bonds.
It has zero hydrogen, so there's
nothing to pull from in the reaction.
So what does that exactly mean?
Well, we are going to have no reaction.
For this step.
So how do we tell what
the pattern is here?
There's a couple ways to do it.
The first one has to do with if you count
the number of hydrogens that are on the
starred carbons, you, it gives you a
hint of how many reactions there are.
So if I go to the first one,
we can see that we had two
hydrogens on that starred species.
Notice how aldehydes went
through two reactions.
Same thing with the starred carbon.
On the secondary there is one hydrogen.
It went through one reaction,
and then with the last one
there was zero hydrogens.
It went through no reactions.
That is one way I have a common
phrase that I like to think of as
well to figure out how far can you go?
And I go off the idea of adding oxygen.
The phrase here, which is
all about adding co bonds.
So when we are looking at these
structures, well, if we want to
add co bonds, if we look at the
first structure, this alcohol up
here in the top left, we had one C
bond versus the second structure.
We had two co bonds that are here, right?
So we went from.
One CO bond, which, uh, so one co
bond to two CO bonds, and now we
have a total of three CO bonds.
So it's going from one to two to three.
Same thing with the secondary.
It goes from one it two CO
bonds, and then the last one.
It doesn't go anywhere.
It just stops at one CO bond.
If there is a trend for how to understand
these, I hope that this video helped in
understanding oxidation and reduction.
Keep practicing it and understanding it.
You will get this down.
It is a big part of biochemistry as
well as organic chemistry, so this
is a basics of oxidation of alcohols.
If you like this video, please hit
the like and subscribe, and I hope
to see you back for future videos.
Bye now.